Hey everyone, welcome to this video
where we're going to take a look at
reranking and how we can use that to
improve the performance of rag or
retrieval augmented generation for very
little effort. If you've been building
basic rack applications like this one uh
and you have a lot of data, you might
have run into problems where it
struggles to fetch the correct sources
even though you're pretty sure the
sources are there. This is actually
quite a common problem. Today, we're
going to address this by adding a
reranking step to our rag pipeline to
boost the quality of our results. It's
really simple to implement as well. It's
really just a single API call. And I've
seen research papers claim that this can
improve your search accuracy by 10 to
30%. Uh, but we're going to try it on
our own pipeline here today as well to
see if it really works. First, I'll show
you how re-ranking works under the hood.
Then we'll add it to an existing rag
pipeline using coher's reranking API.
And we'll finish up by testing it and
seeing if it improved our results. Now,
this video is intended for someone who
is already familiar with Rag. But if you
need a refresher, then check out some of
my previous videos that I've made on
this topic. And here we'll also be
building on top of a simple RG pipeline
application that we built in one of my
previous videos. The links to all of
this will be in the description below.
Let's get started.
Before we get into re-ranking, let's
first take a look at our existing rag
pipeline infrastructure. We have a
pretty standard setup here. Documents
get processed by an indexer module which
splits them into chunks and then stores
them in a vector database with
embeddings. When a query comes in, we
use a retriever to find the relevant
chunks by comparing the embedding values
of the query and the original chunk. uh
and then a response generator uses those
chunks as context for an LLM to create
the final answer. Now the problem really
is in this retrieval step by comparing
the um embedding distance of the query
and uh the different chunks. We don't
really get the best results. So we end
up having to fetch a lot of different
results and hope that the comparison
gets us most of the right results. This
means we usually end up with a mix of
highly relevant and somewhat relevant
chunks. And the problem is that LLMs
have limited context windows and can get
confused when you give it too much
information. So we want to only give it
a few documents. The problem is what if
the one that we actually want is outside
of this number of documents that we
choose as our cutoff point. For example,
if we choose three documents, um it
might turn out that the fifth or the
sixth one is the one we actually want.
This is where re-ranking comes in. It
basically helps you sort out this pile
of information to what is most relevant
to the query itself. Instead, this is
how the process could look with
reranking. So, the first step is that we
still fetch a lot of matching documents
more than the number that we intend to
return to the LLM. And for this, we
still use um vector embedding distance
as a way to find that initial set of
documents. Now, once we have this
smaller set of documents, we could use
reranking. And reranking is a little bit
more expensive, which is why we don't
use it across the whole data set. And
this is just a very very simple um
three-step explanation of how it works.
So in the first step, we use the
distance function to still fetch a bunch
of different documents. And we're going
to fetch more than we intend to return
to the LLM. So for example, if we wanted
to return just three documents to the
LLM, we might choose to fetch 10 or 15
at this initial step. In the second
step, we use our reranking algorithm. So
out of these initial documents, we will
actually find a better ordering for them
according to what's most relevant to the
query. And I'll show you how that works
later. But finally once we have this
ordering we can pick the three or
whatever number of the top relevant
documents from the initial set. So we
basically get higher quality results and
have a higher chance to get the document
that we really really need. And the way
we're going to do that is that we're
just going to add an additional
re-ranking step to our pipeline. And you
can think of it mostly just as another
step within the retrieval process. Now
to understand why and how re-ranking
works, let's first take a look at the
problem with traditional vector search
in a little bit more detail. With
traditional vector search, your document
gets split into little text chunks and
then each of those chunks gets turned
into embeddings ahead of time just like
in this diagram here. And when you make
a query, that query also gets turned
into an embedding. Then we just compare
embeddings using similarity to find
matches. The problem here is that the
document embeddings are created without
any knowledge of what the user might
ask. So the embeddings tend to be a
little bit general. Here's a concrete
example. Let's say you have a document
about Python coding concepts and another
about Python snake habitats. If someone
asks, "How do I install Python?" Then
traditional vector search might rank
both of these highly because they both
contain the word Python. But obviously
only the coding document is actually
relevant to that query. This is where
reranking is supposed to help. Instead
of relying on precomputed embeddings, a
re-ranker can look at the actual query
text and the actual document text
together and make a much smarter
decision about relevance. So how does
reranking do that under the hood? Well,
it uses something called cross-
encoding. To explain it in a very
simplified way, it basically combines
the query and the source text first
before processing it with a transformer.
This is different to traditional rack
vector search which process the query
and the text separately and then uses a
distance function to compare those
results. The re-ranking approach
actually lets the system pick up on
subtle cues like whether the query is
asking about a technical process or
general information or if the user wants
recent data versus historical context.
And when the query has multiple possible
interpretations uh it tries to figure
out which one makes the most sense. Now,
the trade-off is that this approach is
much slower than traditional vector
search because it has to process each
query document pair individually. You
can't premputee anything. Every
evaluation happens at runtime. To work
around this limitation, we could use a
two-staged approach. Um, for example,
let's say that we have 10,000 documents
in our database. We can first start by
using vector search, which is much
faster to get maybe the top 100
candidate documents. And then we can use
the slower but more accurate reranker to
pick the top 10 most relevant ones. And
those are the ones that will send to the
LLM. Now, in reality, LLM context
windows these days are really, really
huge. You could probably fit in your
entire document database. Um, we're
talking context windows of 100K to a
million tokens are now pretty much the
norm, and it will probably continue to
grow in the future. So before you try
any of this stuff, you could see if you
could just pass in all of your documents
in the database and see if it actually
gets you your answer. However,
re-ranking might still be effective if
you are constrained, like you have a lot
of other contexts you want to use or if
you just want to optimize and use fewer
tokens when you invoke your LLM. Okay,
now let's look at a practical example of
how we can add this to an existing rag
pipeline. For this, I'm going to use the
simple rag pipeline project that I've
built, which you can find on GitHub. I
also have a separate video covering this
in more detail if you want to walk
through how it was built. Now, all of
the individual components of this
pipeline are implemented as a separate
Python class. This is all hooked up in
this rag pipeline class here as well.
So, you could see all of these
components being added and connected
together. Now, the great thing about
this project is that it's designed with
modular components. So, adding reranking
is pretty straightforward. All we have
to do is update the retriever component.
So let's take a look at our current
retriever implementation. And as you can
see, this is pretty basic. It just
delegates to our databases search
method. And it does that to find the top
five most similar chunks to the queries
embedding. But now we can make this a
little bit smarter by adding reranking.
And here's our upgraded version. So now
we're following the two-stage approach I
mentioned before. First, we retrieve
more documents than we actually need. In
this case, three times as many. So if
our top K is five, we're actually going
to fetch 15 documents from our database.
This will give the reranker more
candidates to choose from. Then we will
pass those results to a re-ranking
method that will select the most
relevant ones. Now, we haven't
implemented this re-ranking function
yet. So let's go ahead and do that next.
For the actual re-ranking, we're going
to use Coher's re-ranking API. Coher has
some really effective re-ranking models,
and their API is also really easy to
use. You'll first have to go to their
website and then get an API key. Next,
you'll also need to install the coher
library into your Python environment.
Here's the command to do that using pip.
And when you are here in the dashboard
creating an API key, just note that you
can create production keys or trial
keys. So, if you want to try for free,
then create a trial key. Now, back to
our project. This is how we can
implement the reranking. Uh let's walk
through what's happening here. First, we
create a cohhere client and then call
their rerank API. We pass in the users
query and all the document chunks that
we've retrieved and specify how many top
results we want back. Coher's model will
analyze each document in the context of
this specific query and then returns a
ranked list. The response includes the
indices of the original document ranked
by the relevance score. Once you have
your API key, set it up in your
environment variable so that your coher
library can pick it up. Here's what an
output from this process would actually
look like. So here we have a bunch of
reranked indices 7 2 0 and 12. This
means that out of the 15 original
documents that we looked at, these
indices are the top five most relevant
in this order. So here document number
seven in our original set would actually
be the top relevant document followed by
document 2 15 0 and 12 in that order. So
now we have a smaller set of more
relevant documents that we can use for
the next step in our rack pipeline. Now
let's actually see this in action in our
rack pipeline application. We actually
have built-in evaluation tools so that
we can easily measure improvements. I've
also added a flag so that we can run the
same evaluation with reranking and
without it really easily. Now in this
project, I've already run the command to
chunk and embed my documents. So my
database is ready to go. Let's run the
evaluation first uh without the
re-ranking flag enabled.
And just to remind you how uh the
evaluation works in this application, we
have a sample question set of 30 pairs
of questions and answers uh that is
based on some of these original document
PDFs here. So this has all been chunked
and embedded for us in our vector
database. And now we're testing to see
whether our system can find the right
answer to these questions.
And so without re-ranking enabled, we
could see that the total score is 24 out
of 30.
And if we scroll up to see how it's
actually done this work, uh we could see
that during the retrieval process, it
just takes the top five results that it
finds based on each query. So now let's
clear that out and run it again. This
time with the reranking flag enabled.
And just to show you inside the code, uh
this re-ranking flag here is basically
just uh a boolean that is passed to our
search function. If it's turned on, then
what we do is we triple our search
results using vector search. And then we
rerank them and return the top K. Uh if
it's not turned on, we just return the
top K from the vector search itself. So
let's go back to the terminal and run
this. And here is the result. We now
score 27 out of 30. So with reranking we
were able to get a slight bump in the
results. It's still not perfect but it
was a pretty easy improvement. And if we
scroll up into the log we could also see
that uh the reranking is actually
working as intended. So here it's
reanking the indices uh which is not the
same as the original order that vector
search would have found them in. In this
example because we only want to return
five results. Uh, with traditional
vector search, we would have missed out
on documents six and nine. It's not
going to change the world, but most of
the time you want as many improvements
as you can get. Um, I'm going to have to
be honest with you as well. I did have
to edit my Q&A sample set a little bit
just to have the type of questions that
re-ranking would really help to improve.
And likewise, in a real world use case,
I think re-ranking would definitely have
a bigger effect in some data set than
others. Now, as I mentioned at the start
of the video, context windows have
become so big for LLMs these days that
you might not even need re-ranking at
all. You might just be able to put
everything into that context window and
then get the result that you want. So,
it's up to you whether this is a
technique that you want to implement.
And if you did want to implement this,
then here's a couple of trade-offs you
have to be aware of. Every re-ranking
call is an additional API request, and
that will have some overhead. uh you
might see response times increase from a
few hundred milliseconds to 1 to 2
seconds. Second, there's cost. Ranking
APIs will charge per request, so you
need to factor that into your economics.
Uh the good news is that the cost is
usually quite cheap and likely to get
cheaper over time. And third, there's
the dependency on an external service.
So in this project, we're now relying on
coher's API availability. For production
systems, you might want to implement
some graceful fallback. For most RAG
applications though, the accuracy
improvement is worth the trade-off. Your
users probably prefer getting the right
answer in two seconds than getting a
wrong answer in half a second. Now, we
went through this pretty quickly, so if
you want to dive deeper into the code,
then do check out this GitHub link in
the description where you can find the
full project. The key takeaway here is
that reranking is one of the most
effective ways to slightly improve your
rag accuracy with relatively little
engineering effort. Again, you will have
to trade it off whether it's worth
implementing at all or whether you can
get away with just throwing all of your
documents into that context window. If
you have any questions or comments, let
me know in the description. I hope this
was useful and I'll see you in the next
one.